Guide to the North Carolina Student Rural Health Coalition, Duke University Chapter Records, 1988-2001
University Archives Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
North Carolina Student Rural Health Coalition, Duke University Chapter records 1988-2001
University Archives, Duke University
North Carolina Student Rural Health Coalition. Duke University Chapter.
2 Linear Feet 2,500 Items
The first Student Rural Health Coalition began at Vanderbilt University in 1968. In 1978, the Lyndhurst Foundation began funding similar work in North Carolina with the goal of improving the health conditions of eastern North Carolina, the state's most impoverished and medically underserved region.
Collection contains records pertaining to the operations and activities of the Duke University Chapter of the North Carolina Student Rural Health Coalition with the inclusive dates 1988-2001. Material includes correspondence and memoranda, material relating to internships and cooperative programs with North Carolina Central University, staff work plans and evaluations, reports and surveys, and various printed material.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the University Archives to use this collection.
Provenance
The Duke Chapter of the North Carolina Student Rural Health Coalition records were received by the University Archives as a transfer prior to 2007.
Historical Note
The first Student Rural Health Coalition began at Vanderbilt University in 1968 and focused on improving community health in the Black Belt region. In 1978, the Lyndhurst Foundation began funding similar work in North Carolina with the goal of improving the health conditions of eastern North Carolina, the state's most impoverished and medically underserved region.
In 1987-1988, community representatives and Coalition members formed the cooperative Community Health Collective (CHC) to develop community controlled institutions to address health needs and organize to examine and confront power structures affecting local health conditions. The interaction coalesced around local People's Health Clinics. Health volunteers from Duke University and East Carolina University formed direct relationships with Fremont (Wayne County) and Tillery (Halifax County). The Duke Medical School Chapter provided medical support to the Fremont-area People's Clinic. In 1989, undergraduates from Duke University and North Carolina Central University began active involvement with the Coalition. In 1991-1992, People's Clinics were opened in Garysburg (Northampton County) and Shiloh (Wake County).
Currently, the Duke Chapters of the NCSRHC operate five community health clinics, offer a pre-career health internship program that places students in rural, impoverished areas of North Carolina, and contributes to environmental justice work.
Collection Overview
Contains material pertaining to the operation and activities of the Duke University Chapter of the North Carolina Student Rural Health Coalition, 1988-2001. Material present includes correspondence and memoranda, reports, student surveys, material pertaining to internships and cooperative programs with North Carolina Central University, staff program evaluations and plans of work, and assorted printed material. Printed material includes publicity flyers and mailings advertising Health Fairs and People's Clinics; local, regional, and national newsletters, journals, and clippings concerning health care, community health, race, and economic conditions. Prominent subjects include grant organizations such as the Kathleen Price Bryan Family Fund and MacArthur Foundation, Concerned Citizens of Tillery, Shiloh, North Carolina, and Community Health Collective.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Discrimination in medical care -- North Carolina
Poor -- Medical care -- North Carolina
Public Welfare -- North Carolina
Poverty -- Research -- North Carolina.
North Carolina -- Economic conditions
North Carolina Student Rural Health Coalition
Quality of Health Care -- economics -- North Carolina
Rural health services -- North Carolina
Rural poor -- Medical care -- North Carolina
Related Material
Eva J. Salber Papers, 1937-1990
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
North Carolina Poverty Project records, 1983-2004 and undated (bulk 1986-1997)
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
George R. Parkerson records, 1972-1995
Duke University Medical Archives
Samuel L. Katz papers, 1969-2005
Duke University Medical Archives
Community and Family Medicine Collection
Duke University Medical Archives
Contents of Collection
- Container List, 2 boxes
  - North Carolina Central University (NCCU) internships, 2000-2001 (Box 1)
  - NCCU interns, spring 1999
  - NCCU internships, spring 1999
  - NCCU internships, 1999, (2 folders)
  - NCCU internships, summer 1998
  - NCCU interns, fall 1998
  - NCCU internship-background, 1998, undated
  - Extra internship presentation materials, NCCU, 1998
  - Staff resumes and Board, 1999
  - NCSRHC, NCCU Chapter, undated
  - Duke Med discussion group readings, fall 1999, (2 folders)
  - Shiloh
    - 1994-1998, (2 folders)
    - 1990s
    - Central, 1997-1998
    - Central/Shiloh, 1990s, (2 folders)
    - Durham Morning Herald articles (Shiloh), 1988-1989
    - Shiloh Meetings, 1993 June
    - Shiloh/NCCU newsletter, 1992-1993
    - Shiloh articles, Cary Times/N & O [microfiche and copy], 1988-1989
    - Shiloh People's Clinic Conference, 1994 April
  - Community Health Collective update, 2001 April
  - Robin Ellis's work, 1999
  - Various staff work plans, evaluations, etc., 1989-1994
  - Intern activities report, 1993-1994
  - Concerned Citizens of Tillery, Inc. annual report, 1990
  - NCSRHC
    - annual report, 1983-1984
    - history, undated
  - Miscellaneous, 1990-2001, (2 folders)
  - Miscellaneous, 1990-2001 (Box 2)
  - Camelot, 1993-1997
  - Student surveys, 1994-2000, (2 folders)
  - Student work plans, 1998-1999
  - Organizations in the South-general, 1998
  - Staff retreat, 1999
  - Steve Bader
    - Reports, 1997-1999
    - Sabbatical grant, 1996 Dec.
  - Grant staff, 1997-1999
  - MacArthur Foundation report, 1999
  - Coalitions Connections [newsletter], 2000 Jan.
  - Robin Ellis, progress reports, 1997-1998
  - Grant writing resources, 1995-1996
  - Grant history and funding resources, 1990s
  - CD grant, Gertrude Skelly, 1997-1998
  - Bryan Family Fund, 1997-1999
  - Duke Undergraduates, 1997-1999, (2 folders)
  - Various grants, 1990s
  - Chapter organizer thoughts, 1994-1996
  - Break for a Change, 2001, undated
  - Administrative info, miscellaneous, undated
  - Coordinator's Manual, 1994
  - Organizational model/vision, 1992-1995
  - Ready to call list, undated
  - Keysville Health Fair report, 1988 Nov.
  - Contributions/donations, undated
  - Mailing/Phonathon, undated, (2 folders)
  - Phonathon call list, undated
  - Miscellaneous, 1999-2000, undated
  - Photographs, undated